A Guide to the Dorothy I. Parker papers FA417
Rockefeller Archive Center
Dorothy I. Parker papers
1932-1985
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
Parker, Dorothy
FA417
12.52 Cubic Feet 28 letter document boxes, 4 legal document boxes.
32 document boxes.
Acronyms Used
Acronym Key AAAS American Association for the Advancement of Science; AALDI Association of Agricultural Librarians and Documentalists in India; AIBDA Asociacion Interamericana de Bibliotecarios y Documentalistas Agricolas (Interamerican Association of Agricultural Librarians and Documentalists); AID Agency for International Development (U.S. Department of State); CGIAR Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research; CIMMYT Centro Internacional de Mejoramiento de Maiz y Trigo (International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center); IAALD International Association of Agricultural Librarians and Documentalists; IADS International Agricultural Development Service; IAP Indian Agricultural Program; IARI Indian Agricultural Research Institute; ICA Instituto Colombiano Agropêcuario (Colombian Farming Institute); ICAR Indian Council of Agricultural Research; ICRISAT International Crops Research Institute for the Semi-Arid Tropics; IDRC International Development Research Center; IICA Instituto Interamericano de Ciencias Agricolas (Inter-American Institute of Agricultural Sciences); IITA International Institute of Tropical Agriculture; INCAP Institute of Nutrition of Central America and Panama; IRRI International Rice Research Institute; NAL National Agricultural Library
Biographical/Historical note
Dorothy Inez Parker was born on January 23, 1910 in Traders Point, Indiana. She attended Butler University and received a B.S. in 1932. In 1934, at the University of Cincinnati, she earned her master's degree in Botany. Two years later, she completed work on her doctorate at the same institution.
At Brenau College, Dr. Parker served as the head of the Department of Biology from 1936 to 1938. In 1938, she returned to her alma mater, the University of Cincinnati, as the Instructor of Plant Ecology. After one year, Dr. Parker left the position to become the head of the Department of Biology at St. Mary's College in Indiana and to teach botany. After holding this position from 1939 to 1942, Parker transferred to the University of Notre Dame, serving as the assistant curator of the herbarium and the assistant editor of the "American Midland Naturalist." In 1945, Dr. Parker left the teaching field and began her work with the Rockefeller Foundation. This arrangement lasted for nearly three decades. At the start of this career, Parker worked as a bibliographer and librarian for the Mexican Agricultural Program, editing publications and being in charge of the library. From 1945 to 1958, Parker was stationed in Mexico, supporting the organization of agricultural and university libraries and training library staffs across Latin America. She also helped found the Latin American Association of Agricultural Librarians. From 1959 to 1960, Dr. Parker worked as a library advisor with the Indian Agricultural Program, focusing most of her attention on the establishment of a library wing at the Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) in New Delhi.
In May 1960, Dr. Parker became Assistant Director for Agricultural Sciences at the Rockefeller Foundation's New York office. She was the first woman to be appointed to this position at the Foundation. Shortly thereafter, in 1963, she was promoted to Associate Director, a position she held until retirement in 1970. From 1960 to 1970, Dr. Parker was in charge of the library projects associated with all of the Foundation's programs. During this period, Parker continued to travel extensively through Europe, Asia, and Latin America, having a lasting impact on the agricultural and library science fields across the world.
In 1963, the Rockefeller Foundation published the International Bibliography of Rice Research with the International Rice Research Institute (IRRI). This was done by the Foundation at Dr. Parker's suggestion. In 1967, Parker returned to India at the request of the Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR). While there, she spent most of her time visiting and assessing agricultural universities and institutes which operated under the auspices of ICAR. She then compiled her assessments into a 243-page final report.
Although Dr. Parker officially retired from the Rockefeller Foundation in June 1970, she continued to work as a special consultant for the Agricultural Sciences at the Rockefeller Foundation, attending conferences and workshops. She served as a consultant to an important scientific conference of the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT) and completed work with the Foundation's Cotton Project to analyze and gather information regarding the situation of world cotton. Upon receipt of a grant through the International Development Research Center (IDRC), Parker attended a meeting of the West African Agricultural Librarians and Documentalists through the International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA). Also after retirement, she worked as a consultant for the Agency for International Development (AID), a division of the U.S. Department of State. She attended and participated in multiple conferences through AID.
Throughout her career, Dr. Parker was a distinguished author. Some of her most notable publications include Primer for Agricultural Libraries (April 1968), Library Report for the Indian Council on Agricultural Research (March 1969) and Guide for an Agricultural Library Survey for Developing Countries (1970).
Along with these outstanding achievements, Dr. Parker received many honors throughout her lifetime. She received postdoctoral fellowships to travel and research North American plant geography. Parker was also awarded a two-year postdoctoral fellowship by the American Association of University Women. She became an honorary member of the Asociacion Interamericana de Bibliotecarios y Documentalistas Agricolas (AIBDA) and served as the honorary president for their 1968 conference in Bogotá. Parker also served as a member of the executive committee of the International Association of Agricultural Librarians and Documentalists (IAALD). In addition, Parker was a fellow of both the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) and the Indiana Academy of Science. Parker was also elected to the Board of Trustees of The Western College, a small women's college in Ohio that later became part of Miami University.
Although she devoted most of her life's work to agricultural libraries and other library improvement programs, Dr. Parker set some time aside for herself and her hobbies. After retirement, she spent a month in Florence, Italy, restoring rare manuscripts and books damaged by flood waters. She also became a skilled bookbinder, a craft which she had studied in Mexico City and Florence. Her leather-bound books were beautifully decorated with intricate gold tooling and inlaid stones. In fact, Parker likely bound several of the volumes that are included in this collection. Through her lifetime, she also found interest in the arts, becoming a talented pipe organist and clarinetist and practicing her skill as a charcoal and watercolor sketch artist.
Dorothy Parker died at her home in White Plains, New York on July 30, 1999.
Scope and Contents note
Most of the material in this collection is related to the Rockefeller Foundation. With Dr. Parker's work spanning almost three decades, these papers demonstrate her dedication to the Foundation and its mission. Her efforts spanned the globe, as shown in the documents from Latin America, Europe, Asia, and elsewhere. Parker's influence on the Rockefeller Foundation's Agricultural Program can be seen in the collection, as well as her impact on libraries across the world. She kept detailed records of her travels, assignments, and library plans, all of which reveal much about her personality and character.
Few items in the collection shed light on Parker's life outside work, but this in fact reveals her sheer dedication to the agricultural and library sciences. Dr. Parker was a talented and accomplished woman who became highly respected at the Foundation, especially for being such an ambitious woman. Her expertise in multiple academic fields was respected by professional organizations across the world. Her work continued beyond her retirement, not only with the Rockefeller Foundation, but with other organizations as well as the U.S. Government. The collection spans from the late 1930s, when Parker finished her schooling, and continues through retirement into the early 1980s.
Arrangement note
The Dorothy I. Parker Papers are arranged into 6 series, several of which are divided into subseries. With only a few exceptions, the folders are organized alphabetically by folder title. Within folders, documents are arranged chronologically.
Series 1 - Rockefeller Foundation (1938-1985): Subseries 1: General Correspondence Subseries 2: Publications Subseries 3: Assignments- Latin America, Mexican Agricultural Program Subseries 4: Assignments- Latin America, Agricultural Program Subseries 5: Assignments- Asia, Indian Agricultural Program (IAP) Subseries 6: Assignments- Asia, International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) Subseries 7: Assignments- Asia, Other Libraries Subseries 8: Library Programs- Other Subseries 9: Post-Retirement- Cotton Project Subseries 10: Post-Retirement- Other Subseries 11: Rockefeller Foundation Programs- Other
Series 2 - U.S. Government Departments and Programs (1962-1981) Subseries 1: Department of Agriculture Subseries 2: Department of State - Agency for International Development (AID) Subseries 3: Other
Series 3 - United Nations (1974-1975)
Series 4 - Friends and Colleagues (1957-1979)
Series 5 - Professional Organizations (1955-1981) Subseries 1: Asociacion Interamericana de Bibliotecarios y Documentalistas Agricolas (AIBDA) Subseries 2: Instituto Interamericano de Ci.encias Agricolas (IICA) Subseries 3: International Association of Agricultural Librarians and Documentalists (IAALD) Subseries 4: Other
Series 6 - Miscellaneous/Ephemera (1932-1978)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Dorothy Parker began donating her records to the Rockefeller Archive Center in August 1972. Through continued donations from Parker and the former Rockefeller Foundation president, Dr. J. George Harrar, the Archive Center was able to expand the breadth of the collection over the years. The collection was donated to the RAC in June 1987.
Related Archival Materials note
Rockefeller Foundation records, RG 6.13 - Field Offices, Mexico Rockefeller Foundation records, RG 6.9 - Field Offices, Cali, Colombia (1960-1978) Rockefeller Foundation records, RG 12 - Officers' Diaries, Dorothy Parker Diaries (1960-1969) Rockefeller Foundation records, RG 13 - Oral Histories, Dorothy Parker – Rockefeller Foundation Agriculture Program (1967)
Separated Materials note
Commercially published books have been separated and housed in the RAC library.
However, one commercially published book, the "International Bibliography of Rice Research", remains in the collection because it represents Parker's work, and is directly related to the bibliography supplements in Series 1, Subseries 6.
Related Archival Materials note
1. E.C. Stakman Papers (University of Minnesota) 2. Reminisces of Elvin Charles Stakman: oral history, 1970 (Columbia University, Call Number NXCP88-A278) 3. Reminisces of J. George Harrar: oral history, 1972-1977 (Columbia University, Call Number NXCP88-A1564) 4. National Agricultural Library Digital Repository. 5. Society of Woman Geographers (Records - Library of Congress).
Agricultural innovations -- Mexico; Library administration; Agricultural administration; Agricultural education -- Developing countries; Agricultural education -- Mexico; Agricultural innovations
- Rockefeller Foundation, 1938-1985; 1
  Arrangement
  Series 1 is arranged into 11 subseries:
  Subseries 1: General Correspondence; Subseries 2: Publications; Subseries 3: Assignments: Latin America, Mexican Agricultural Program; Subseries 4: Assignments: Latin America, Agricultural Program; Subseries 5: Assignments: Asia, Indian Agricultural Program (IAP); Subseries 6: Assignments: Asia, International Rice Research Institute (IRRI); Subseries 7: Assignments: Asia, Other Libraries; Subseries 8: Library Programs- Other; Subseries 9: Post-Retirement: Cotton Project; Subseries 10: Post-Retirement: Other; Subseries 11: Rockefeller Foundation Programs: Other
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1 consists of eleven subseries, all of which are related to Rockefeller Foundation programs and/or Dorothy Parker's work with the Foundation.
  Subseries 1 General Correspondence, consists of correspondence between Parker and Rockefeller Foundation individuals from 1945-1973. There are also library inquiries and information gathered in response to these inquiries.
  Subseries 2, Publications, contains published materials from 1956-1985, which are related to Rockefeller Foundation programs, people, or grantees. Included in this subseries are reports, bibliographies, and publications written by Rockefeller Foundation employees. There are a few publications which do not have an apparent connection with the Rockefeller Foundation, yet upon closer review, they do. One is the Ford Foundation Annual Report, which mentions and describes collaboration between the Rockefeller Foundation and Ford.
  Subseries 3, Assignments: Latin America, Mexican Agricultural Program, consists of materials related to Dorothy Parker's early career as a Rockefeller Foundation bibliographer and librarian in Mexico. These include publications and program papers from the Office of Special Studies, where Parker worked in Mexico. Parker worked with the Mexican Agricultural Program from 1945 to 1958. These materials span from 1938 to 1960.
  Subseries 4, Assignments: Latin America, Agricultural Program, contains papers from Parker's work in Latin America, other than in Mexico. These range from travel schedules to correspondence, including library plans and publications. Most of the materials pertain to Parker's work in Colombia, but some relate to library projects in Guatemala, Costa Rica, and Peru. The materials range from 1950 to 1974.
  Subseries 5, Assignments: Asia, Indian Agricultural Program (IAP), contains materials from the Indian Agricultural Program. Parker was stationed in India from 1959-1960 and during 1967. Included in this subseries are reports, drafts, and library improvement plans. The documents span from 1958 to 1973.
  Subseries 6, Assignments: Asia, International Rice Research Institute (IRRI), contains numerous bibliographies, bibliography supplements, and publications. The primary publication, the International Bibliography of Rice Research, was published by the Rockefeller Foundation at Parker's suggestion. Other items relate to the planning of the IRRI Library in 1963. The materials range from 1960 to 1979.
  Subseries 7, Assignments: Asia, Other Libraries, contains materials pertaining to library projects at three universities in Asia: Kasetsart University, Keio University, and the University of Philippines. These papers, from 1964-1974, pertain to Parker's work with the universities' libraries.
  Subseries 8, Library Programs: Other, contains items from other library projects, some of which were agricultural libraries. Some of these resources may have been references for Parker's own library projects. Reports and miscellaneous travel information for other library programs are included in this subseries. Some documents were placed in this subseries because they are from the post-retirement period. The documents range from 1955 to 1979.
  Subseries 9, Post-Retirement: Cotton Project, consists of items relating to the Rockefeller Foundation's Cotton Project, for which Parker was a consultant after her retirement. Many of these materials were collected by Parker as resources for the project. These include publications, pamphlets, and reports about textiles and cotton production. Meeting notes and travel information are included in this subseries. The materials span from 1940 to 1975.
  Subseries 10, Post-Retirement: Other, includes miscellaneous, post-retirement consultant work for the Rockefeller Foundation and other Foundation-funded programs. Parker retired in 1970, so these materials include papers from conferences, seminars, and workshops after 1970. In 1975, through a grant from the International Development Research Center (IDRC), Parker attended an International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA) conference. All materials related to these programs, ranging from 1968-1981, are included in this subseries.
  Subseries 11, Rockefeller Foundation Programs: Other, includes materials from Rockefeller Foundation Programs that were not directly related to Dorothy Parker's work. In most instances, Parker was given this material after retirement because it was related to her line of work, yet she had no apparent part in the programs themselves. The documents span from 1973 to 1981.
  - General Correspondence, 1.1
    - Harrar, J. George, 1945-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Harrar, J. George, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Harrar, J. George, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Harrar, J. George, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Information Collected for Library Inquiries, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Christensen, J. J., University of Minnesota, 1957
      - Colwell, W. E., 1955
      - Eli Lilly and Company, 1956
      - Lamkin, Burton E., 1973
      - Scholars and Foundation Employees, 1957
      - Stakman, E. C., 1965
    - Rockefeller Foundation Home and Field Offices, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Publications, 1.2
    - Africa - Cassava Information Center, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Agricultural Research - CGIAR (Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Annual Reports, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Book Reviews of "To Feed This World", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Conference and Workshop Working Papers, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Scope and Contents note
      "Changing Roles of Women in Industrial Societies", 1977. "Society, Culture and Agriculture", 1978.
    - Discussion Paper - Agricultural Development, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Equal Opportunity Program, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Ford Foundation - Annual Report, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Harrar, J. George, 1963-1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - National Research Council Study on Africa, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1956-1960 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Manual and informative pamphlets.
      - "The Millets and Minor Cereals": Bibliography, 1974
        Separated Materials
        Separated to RAC Library.
      - "The Millets", Bibliography, 1967
    - Oral History - Parker, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - "Sorghum", Bibliography, 1967
    - Utah State University, Grantee - Bibliography with microfiche, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      "Utah Natural Resources and Land Use Information System"
  - Assignments: Latin America, Mexican Agricultural Program, 1.3
    - Agricultural Studies Booklet, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Draft and Publications, 1950-1960 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Mexican Agricultural Program, 1950; Instituto Politecnico Nacional, 1955; "La Obligaci¢n de la Fitopatolog¡a en el Problema de la Alimentacion Humana", 1960; "The Evolution of Practices and Concepts in Education", 1960.
    - Inquiries about Libraries, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Photograph - Office of Special Studies, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Program Overview (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Publication - Office of Special Studies, 1947-1953 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      Compilation of essays (Nos. 1-12) regarding agriculture and livestock farming; authors include Rupert, Harrar, Borlaug, and Colwell
    - Publication - Office of Special Studies, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      "Primera Asamblea Latinoamericana de la Ciencia del Suelo"
    - Publications - Office of Special Studies, 1947-1950 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      Brochures, Nos. 1-5, 7-11
    - Publications - Office of Special Studies, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      Directory and guide
    - Publications - Office of Special Studies, 1947-1953 (Box 5)
      1947-1953 - Compilation of Technical Pamphlets (Nos. 1-10) from Mexican Agricultural Program; authors include Mangelsdorf, Rupert, Stakman, Harrar, and Wellhausen. 1949-1951 - Compilation of Miscellaneous Pamphlets (Nos. 1-4).
  - Assignments: Latin America, Agricultural Program, 1.4
    - Correspondence - General, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence - Inter-American Institute of Agricultural Sciences, Costa Rica, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Guatemala Library - INCAP (Institute of Nutrition of Central America and Panama), 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Publications, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 33)
      "Agricultural Program of the Rockefeller Foundation" (2 copies)
    - Travels and Library Assignments, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 34)
      Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Costa Rica. Correspondence, itinerary, and visit notes; correspondents include Harrar.
    - Travels and Library Assignments, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 35)
      Ecuador, Peru, Trinidad, Uruguay, Venezuela. Travel Notes.
    - Travels and Library Assignments, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 36)
      Colombian libraries, Peru libraries, travel plans, Venezuela libraries.
    - Final Report of Library Study Committee, Colombia, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - ICA (Instituto Colombiano Agropecuario) Library, Colombia, 1966-1974 (Box 7, Folder 38)
      Correspondence and reports
    - ICA (Instituto Colombiano Agropecuario) Report - Colombia, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - ICA (Instituto Colombiano Agropecuario) Report - Colombia, 1970; Copy 2 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Library School, University of Antioquia, Colombia, 1956-1963 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Medellin and Tibaytata Library Projects, Colombia, 1955-1957 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Assignments: Asia, Indian Agricultural Program (IAP), 1.5
    - Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) Library - Additions and Recommendations (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) Library - Book Selection (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) Library - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) Library - Library Binding and Book Repair (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) Library - Lists of Periodicals and Journals (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) Library - Organization of Library, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) Library - Staff Information and Meeting Minutes (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) Library - Use of Library, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Library Committee Reports, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - Library Science Programs - General Information and Syllabi, 1958-1960 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - Manuscript Report - Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR) and Agricultural University Libraries, 1968; Map included in back of publication. (Box 9, Folder 53)